Preliminary Inventory of the Jiří Horák papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jiří Horák papers
1946-2006
2006C66
Hoover Institution Archives
74 manuscript boxes (29.6 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, bulletins, printed matter, and photographs, relating to socialism in Czechoslovakia, anti-communist political movements, Czech émigré affairs, Radio Free Europe, the Socialist International, and post-1989 political conditions in Czechoslovakia.
Horák, Jiří, 1924-2003.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Czechoslovak social democratic leader; emigre and political scientist in the United States; secretary-general, Council of Free Czechoslovakia, 1974-1994; chairman, Ceskoslovenská Strana Sociálne Demokratická, 1990-1992.
Scope and Content of Collection
Speeches and writings, correspondence, reports, bulletins, printed matter, and photographs, relating to socialism in Czechoslovakia, anti-communist political movements, Czech émigré affairs, Radio Free Europe, the Socialist International, and post-1989 political conditions in Czechoslovakia.
Ceskoslovenská strana sociálně demokratická.; Council of Free Czechoslovakia.; Radio Free Europe.; Socialist International (1951- ); Anti-communist movements.; Czechoslovakia--Politics and government--1989-1992.; Czechs--United States.; Radio broadcasting--Czechoslovakia.; Socialism--Czechoslovakia.
- Part One: February 1948 (Communist Coup in Czechoslovakia) to November 17, 1989 (Fall of Communism to the Velvet Revolution)
  - 1948 (Box 54-56)
    - Ustřední svaz československých studentu v exilu (Central Union of Czechoslovak Students in exile) (Box 54-56)
    - Svaz československých uprchliku v Německu (Union of Czechoslovak Refugees in Germany) (Box 54-56)
    - Americký fond pro československé uprchliky (AFCR -American Fund for Czechoslovak Refugees) (Box 54-56)
    - Jiří Horák - personal file: scholarship in Denmark, documents, photographs, correspondence (Box 54-56)
  - 1955-1969 (Box 31-32)
  - RSC - Rada svobodného Československá (Council of Free Czechoslovakia) (Box 31-32)
    - 1970-1975(I.) (Box 40-42)
    - 1975(II.)-1976 (Box 51-53)
    - 1977 (Box 26-28)
    - 1978-79 (Box 59-61)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 43-45)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 72-74)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 33-35)
    - a. until November 17, 1989 (Box 7-8)
    - b. after November 17, 1989 (Box 7-8)
  - RSC and Washington, 1975 (Box 64-65)
    - Correspondence with the White House, Dept. of State, Senate, Congress, Congressional (Box 64-65)
    - Record, AFUCIO, CSNRA (Československá národni rada americká), etc. (Box 64-65)
  - Jiří Horák -International, 1949 (Box 5-6)
    - a. International meetings and trips to Europe and Asia, lUSY (International Union of Socialist Youth), other youth organizations: trip reports, photographs, correspondence, etc. (Box 5-6)
    - b. FEC (Free Europe Committee) New York (Box 5-6)
  - Jiří Horák, from 1951 on (Box 36-37)
    - a. AFCR -American Fund for Czechoslovak Refugees, New York (Box 36-37)
    - b. Mayor's Ethnic Council, New York (photographs) (Box 36-37)
    - c. BBLA - Bohemian Benevolent and Literary Association ( Česká dobročinná a vzdelavací organizace), New York (Box 36-37)
    - d. contract with JPRS - U.S. Joint Publications Research Service, Washington, D.C. (samples of his research enclosed) (Box 36-37)
  - Jiří Horák, from 1974 on (Box 57-58)
    - a. RFE - Radio Free Europe (Radio svobodná Evropa), Munich, Germany: correspondence, Radio University, scripts, etc. (Box 57-58)
    - b. FEC- Free Europe Committee (Výbor pro svobodnou Evropu), New York, New York: Mailing Project (George Minden) (Box 57-58)
    - c. Communist attacks (Radio Prague); communist agents in the West (Box 57-58)
  - Jiří Horák, from 1953 on (Box 46-48)
    - Columbia University, New York; Manhattan College, New York correspondence, articles, reviews, press (Box 46-48)
    - Doctoral dissertation "The Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party 1938-1945", New York, 1960 (Box 46-48)
    - M.A. thesis:"The Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party 1918-1945", New York) (Box 46-48)
  - RSC - Rada svobodného Československá (Council of Free Czechoslovakia), 1968 (Box 70-71)
    - Charta 77 (I.) Documents and correspondence, Czechoslovak dissident movement (Box 70-71)
  - RSC - Rada svobodného Československá (Council of Free Czechoslovakia), 1968 (Box 68-69)
    - Charta 77 (II.) Documents and correspodence, Czechoslovak dissident movement (Box 68-69)
  - Jiří Horák, 1956 (Box 14-16)
  - "Svědectví" ("Testimony," cultural and political quarterly) some early issues enclosed publisher and member of the editorial board: Jiří Horák, editor: Pavel Tigrid. published first in New York, then in Paris. Distributed in Czechoslovakia as an underground magazine. (Box 62-63)
- Part Two: From November 17, 1989 (Fall of Communism in Czechoslovakia to the Velvet Revolution) (Box 62-63)
  - ČSSD - Československastrana Sociálně Demokratická (Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party) (Box 62-63)
    Scope and Contents note
    Note:Jiří Horák returns to his native Czechoslovakia on December 17, 1989, after 41 years of exile in the USA, and helps to revive the CSSD that was abolished by the Communists in 1948. The CSSD exists since April 7, 1878. This party was also abolished by the Nazis during the WWII., then revived for short three years after the WWII. between 1945-1948, before being abolished again, this time by the Communists in 1948.
    - ČSSD, Nov 17, 1989-1990 (Box 49-50)
      - XXIV. Congress of ČSSD - Jiří Horák elected chairman. He accepts. Announces he will not take any salary during his office as chairman of ČSSD. (Box 49-50)
      - Articles and addresses, interviews, correspondence, agenda, press conferences, Party newspaper "Pravo lidu", photographs, clippings, etc. (Box 49-50)
    - ČSSD, 1991 (I.) (Box 12-13)
    - ČSSD, 1991(II.) (Box 29-30)
      - XXV. Congress of ČSSD - Jiří Horák re-elected chairman. (Box 29-30)
      - Articles and addresses, interviews, correspondence, agenda, press conferences, photos, clippings, etc. (Box 29-30)
    - ČSSD, 1992(I.) (Box 20-22)
    - ČSSD, 1992(II.) (Box 3-4)
      - Articles, clippings, press conferences, party agenda etc. (Box 3-4)
      - Party Monitor (Box 3-4)
    - ČSSD, 1992(III.)-1993/March (Box 1-2)
      - Party press, agenda, articles, correspondence etc. (Box 1-2)
      - XXVI. Congress of ČSSD. (Box 1-2)
        Jiří Horák is not seeking re-election. He delivers his last speech as chairman. Elected honorary chairman. He retires and returns to the USA. The next six years he spends summers in the Czech Republic and winters is Florida where he lives permanently in Englewood. Writes and publishes frequently.
    - ČSSD (Box 17-19)
      - a. Interviews and speeches 1989-2993 (Box 17-19)
      - b. MDH - Masarykovo demokratické hnuti, Prague (Box 17-19)
  - ČSSD/International 1989 (Box 23-25)
    - Attends (51) Socialist International congresses and meetings, as chairman of ČSSD and also as co-chairman of the 51 Committe on East and Central Europe. (Box 23-25)
    - 51 agenda, correspondence, speeches, etc. (Box 23-25)
  - ČSSD/Federal Assembly (Box 66-67)
    - Member of the Federal Assembly; member of the Presidium of the Federal (Box 66-67)
    - Assembly; chairman of the Foreign Committee of the Federal Assembly addresses, documents (Box 66-67)
  - Contains old publications going back before, during and after 1948 (Box 9-11)
  - Personal file (Box 38-39)
    - Manuscripts (notes, short memoirs, political observations and comments) written by hand, presumably during the last years of his life (+July 25, 2003 in Englewood, Florida), were found only in 2004. There are no exact dates given. Manuscripts were retyped by his wife Zdena (original manuscripts are attached to the retyped originals). (Box 38-39)
    - Articles by Jiří Horák. Dozens of articles found and copied from his personal Internet file. Many were published in Czechoslovakia. There are no exact dates when these articles were written (presumably during his retirement), the dates given are the dates when the articles were entered in the Internet file. (Box 38-39)
    - Dated articles by Jiří Horák and correspondence since March 1993 (Box 38-39)
    - Biographical data (Box 38-39)
    - Various biographies from different sources (Box 38-39)
    - Jiří Horák's life story, in his own words, as published in "Svět piny Čechů" (Box 38-39)
    - Biography of Josef Horák, father of Jiří, as published in "Poslední počta" Josef Horák was a Czechoslovak politician who died in exile in New York in 1978. (Box 38-39)
    - Personal documents: Photographs, copies of diplomas, medals and state decorations (Box 38-39)
    - A file in memory of Jiří Horák: Obituaries, press articles, memorial services in the USA and in the Czech Republic. Eulogies (by Professor Radomir Luza, Professor Mojmir Povolny, Professor Stanley Winterset al.) (Box 38-39)